this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
tonight I want to well thank you I want
to begin studying how things change with
time in quantum mechanics we started a
little bit but let me just very quickly
remind you very very quickly again how
they change in time in classical physics
we've discussed over and over and over
and how they change in time for a
discrete system like a coin toss
up down up down up down or heads tails
heads tails heads tails that sort of
thing
always you have to postulate a law of
change a law of evolution and that
corresponds to a set of arrows which
tell you where to move next and so forth
notice that if a system is discrete if
it only has a finite number of states or
a finite number of independent states
then classically the only meaning you
can make of its evolution would have to
be with discrete time intervals where
you would sample the system only in
discrete intervals because there's no
continuous way to go from one to another
heads tails heads tails okay
well certainly classical physics allows
continuous time but in order to have it
we have to go to the Hamiltonian quantum
mechanic or aha sorry excuse me the
classical mechanics of continuous
systems continuous systems means for
example particles which can be anywhere
is on an axis so that the position is
continuous the momentum is continuous
and so forth but still the classical
rules of evolution are predictive and
instead of being hops from one discrete
state to another they become flows flows
in phase space now if you took my class
in classical mechanics so remember what
I'm saying if you didn't think you don't
know what I'm saying it's not going to
be terribly important but I did want to
connect with classical mechanics a
little bit if we have for example a
particle on a line
a particle on a line is characterized by
a position X and either a velocity or
better yet a momentum P and so that
every instant of time it has a position
and a momentum something that we know is
not going to be right in quantum
mechanics but we can describe the
evolution in terms of a flow on this is
called phase space a flow on the phase
space which is simply another way of
saying that if you start the system at
any point a position and a velocity or
momentum it will move in general and it
will move along one of these flow lines
the flow lines are described by a
Hamiltonian and I just want to very
briefly review classical mechanics
extremely briefly the law of evolution
of a classical mechanical system is
through the object that's called the
Hamiltonian and the Hamiltonian is a
function of positions of momenta X's and
peas however many X's and peas there are
there's a p for every X and an X for
every P if there are seven coordinate
sudden particles and the seven times
three coordinates seven times three
momenta but let's just write it as one
coordinate 1 momenta all right that
Hamiltonian determines it is the energy
it is the energy of the system as a
function of positions and momenta as a
function of positions typically it would
give you the potential energy as a
function of momenta it would give you
the kinetic energy so a simple example
for example would be P squared over 2m
for the kinetic energy plus some
potential energy as a function of
position that would be an example the
systems systems have Hamiltonians
the Hamiltonians represent the energy
but they're written in terms of
positions and momenta but the law of
evolution which is a deterministic law
of evolution there's a law which tells
you wherever you start it tells you
where you'll be
after a very brief interval so it's just
described instead of instead of a bunch
of points with arrows connecting them in
some way it becomes a set of flow lines
which tells you wherever you begin where
you go next
all right the equations the mathematical
equations are differential equations the
differential equations which are written
in terms of the Hamiltonian I'm just
going to write them down for you
Hamilton's equations Hamilton's
equations are that the derivative of the
Hamiltonian with respect to momentum
let's just do it here
derivative the Hamiltonian with respect
to momentum in this case would just be
peel the M P over m is velocity momentum
is mass times velocity so P over m is
just velocity and velocity is just the
time derivative of X that's X dot and
the other the other equation is
basically F equals MA the derivative of
the Hamiltonian with respect to position
gives you minus the force that's the
derivative of the potential energy with
respect to positions minus the force and
that's the time rate of change or minus
the time rate of change of the momentum
those are Hamilton's equations now
supposing you have some function let's
call it f an observable function of
position and momentum I call it an
observable because I mean that that you
can make a measurement of it P and X the
x squared plus P squared or whatever it
happens to be and I want to compute its
time derivative all right its time
derivative is given by the derivative of
F with respect to P times the time
derivative of P plus the derivative of F
with respect to X plant the time
derivative of x but we have a formula
for P dot let's go first to X dot we
haven't for
x-dot it's D H by D P so we can write
over here D H by D P and likewise over
here for P dot I'll boy I'm I'm taking
some of this home if you and P dot is D
H by D X this combination given two
functions H and F one of them happens to
be the Hamiltonian here one of them
happens to be some arbitrary observable
but given two functions of X and P this
combination is called the Poisson
bracket you don't have to remember it I
just want you to remember that the time
evolution of things of anything is
gotten by some operation that involves
the Hamiltonian this is called the
Poisson bracket of H this is the Poisson
bracket of F with H and we would write
this the Poisson bracket of H of F with
H and the definition of the Poisson
bracket of two objects is just this
particular combination there is it the
the F by DX the H by G P and so forth
you can read it yourself
given any two things this is the basic
structure of classical mechanics the
Hamiltonian determines a flow it tells
you how X and P change with time so it
determines a flow and if I have any
interesting quantity I can determine how
it changes with time along the flow I
can tell you how it changes with time
along the flow by plus on brackets now
it's not terribly important to know very
much about Poisson brackets the main
point is the Hamiltonian is the
generator of time evolution those are
the words
the Hamiltonian generates the time
evolution of a system the same is true
in quantum mechanics and it's much more
intuitive this to me was always very
obscure you know I learned it I
understood it I know how to use it I
even knew where it came from but it
always seemed like too complicated and
expression here I always thought it was
just something simple it must underlie
it and something simple it does underlie
it what underlies it is quantum
mechanics quantum mechanics is in many
respects simpler and and in many ways
mathematically easier to understand all
right so how do systems evolve with time
what's the basic rule for the evolution
of a system the basic rule is that
relationships between states don't
change with time let's suppose that some
initial state of the system evolves let
the arrow stand for evolves over a
period of time we could put a p here for
indicating a period of time evolves over
a period of time to something that I'll
call you times a and of course you I
intend to mean a unitary operator
unitary we discussed last time what it
meant let me just remind you what
unitary means it means that it times at
our mission conjugate is the unit
operator or that it's hermitian
conjugate is its inverse that's the
definition of a unitary operator all
right so let's suppose that state a
evolves on the time evolution to u times
a and of course we should indicate here
this you should be parameterized by with
how much time T is the amount of time
which evolved some operation or some
operator which acts on the state initial
state to
the state after time T so here it is
after time T let's suppose the same
thing is true that if we started with
state B after the same evolution of
course we would just write the same
thing you are not quite the same thing
we will write the action of we can call
this the evolution operator let's give
it a name the evolution operator acts on
a to give whatever a becomes it acts on
B to give whatever B becomes alright now
let me write this second equation in
terms of bra vectors in terms of bra
vectors it becomes B evolves now we have
the complex conjugate B is as the her as
the is the conjugate or the bra vector
in order to conjugate we must do
something with is you namely we have to
replace it by its hermitian conjugate if
you like bra vectors are sort of complex
conjugates of ket vectors and hermitian
conjugate sub operators are complex
conjugates of the original operators so
this is the operation of conjugation all
right well what happens now to the inner
product of a with B we started with two
possible states which have some
relationship between them the
relationship simply is codified by the
inner product between them B with a if B
is orthogonal to a they're surely
different if B is parallel to a they're
the same state and if B and a overlap
then anything which is certain in B has
a certain probability of occurring if
you're in the state vector a and vice
versa so this is the basic relationship
mathematical relationship between states
what the inner product there between
them is let's see what happens to it
after a period of time after a period of
time this goes to
let's have it come out over here after a
period of time it goes to know what
happens to be B becomes u dagger times B
that's what happens to B and a becomes u
times a if we insist that the
relationships between vectors are
preserved with time if you want to
picture this in your head think of these
vectors is evolving in time the state
vectors evolve in time but keeping the
angles between them fixed in other words
the whole space of state sort of rotates
that's the way you can think about it
with all vectors and relationships
the relationships between vectors being
kept fixed in that case that tells you
that B a must equal B u dagger u a for
all a and B the implication the
mathematical implication of that is that
U is unitary that u dagger times U is
just the unit operator alright so that's
the that's the fundamental underlying
principle of time evolution of state
vectors in quantum mechanics
it's the governing principle that things
which are orthogonal stay orthogonal
that's it that's really yet in fact
that's enough to to ensure all of this
states which are orthogonal stay
orthogonal things which are
fundamentally dissimilar so dissimilar
that you can tell the difference between
them in a single experiment stay that
way good all right now let's study this
object U of T let's write a more general
equation let's write an equation in the
following way let's suppose we start at
time T and we have at time T we have a
system with a state vector sy of T it
could be a particle on a line it could
be our friend the photon polarization
but it's a state vector at time T P
eventually becomes T plus
t capital T the system has evolved
through an amount of time capital T so
it follows it's just a special
application of what I've written up
there that sigh of T evolves - or let's
say yeah let's let's let me write it
this way yeah let me write it a special
way after a time capital T the system
has evolved the sigh of T plus capital T
new time is T plus capital T amount of
time capital T is evolved and that
according to what we've written up there
must just be u of capital T times sy of
small T all it says is we want to push
the system ahead by an amount of time
capital T we do it by applying the
evolution operator U of capital T so
that's the first fact that's the first
thing time evolution to a certain amount
of time is governed by a unitary
operator next let's see what we can
learn about this what happens if capital
T is 0 if capital T is 0 that's no
evolution at all if there's no evolution
at all then you must be the unit
operator in other words if capital T was
0 then sigh of T plus capital T had
better just be sigh of the original T
the implication of that is U of 0 no
evolution at all is just a unit the
identity operator it does nothing it
leaves the state unchanged all right so
that's the first fact now supposing one
way of finding out how systems evolve is
to let them evolve through very very
short time intervals if we want to get
from time T to time T plus delta T or
time T plus capital T we can break up
that capital T into a lot of little time
intervals and evolve it over once more
all the time interval then another small
time interval then another small time
interval so an interesting question then
is what is you of a very small kind
interval if we know what you is for a
very small time interval we can compound
it together and find out how a system
evolves over a finite time interval so
let's say you of epsilon epsilon me here
means a very small time technically it's
a small enough time that I can ignore
things quadratic in epsilon I can work
the first order in epsilon and that's
what I'm going to do the first order in
epsilon what can I say about you of
Epsilon when epsilon is small
well the zeroth order in other words
when epsilon is zero we should just
write down one and then there's a small
correction to that one if epsilon is
small the correction is small so let's
stand right down epsilon times something
something which has which can we could
just call it L or s for something I'm
going to write it in a very peculiar way
but the reason for it will become
obvious later this is entirely a
convention this is entirely a convention
but I'm going to write it as I think - I
think you are one of minus sign yes I
want a minus sign and I an epsilon I
that's the important things the epsilon
and I'm going to write H divided by
Planck's constant now there's no content
to all of this I and H bar here it can
all be absorbed into the definition of
capital H I've written it that way
because later on we're going to find out
that capital H has a significance as the
energy of the system or the quantum
analog of the Hamiltonian but for the
moment this is just an arbitrary
convention that I put an eye there we'll
see in a moment why the eye is there the
fact that plunks constant is in the
denominator
that's purely definition purely
definition of capital H there's no
content in it yet it's uh it's just
putting the small quantity that goes
into quantum mechanics it's putting it
into the formula in order that later on
we will recognize this thing as a
certain classical object all right let's
see what we can learn about capital H
here we have to have that U of epsilon
or u dagger of epsilon times U of
epsilon to first order in epsilon we're
working with keeping things to first
order in epsilon and only to first order
that should be equal to one let's write
it out what is U dagger well let's write
down u dagger over here u dagger is
equal to one plus I epsilon over h-bar
times the hermitian conjugate of H when
u hermitian conjugate something you have
to change all the coefficients you have
the complex conjugate all the
coefficients I epsilon becomes my I
epsilon becomes minus I epsilon minus I
epsilon becomes I Epsilon and when u
hermitian conjugate you have two
hermitian conjugate the operators
alright so this is the formula for u
dagger so let's write it out one plus I
epsilon over H bar H times one minus I
epsilon over H bar times H has to be
equal to one one meaning the unit
operator and of course one here also
means the unit operator this is an
operator equation H dagger which one
this one I think H dagger here all right
we multiply it out one times one is one
that's going to cancel this one anything
of water epsilon squared is too small to
worry about to the first order
and the only thing that we have will be
an AI epsilon over h-bar and then from
here times 1 will have H bar sorry H
dagger but from 1 times here we will
have minus H 1 times the minus H and
then the H stager times the 1 those are
the two terms that appear here oh we
left out the 1 1 times 1 is 1
but that cancels the 1 here so the
result is the condition that you be
unitary is the condition that H dagger
equals H or H dagger minus H equals 0
same thing as saying H dagger equals H
in other words whatever H is it has to
equal its own hermitian conjugate that
of course is the condition that h is
hermitian so what we learn from this
basic principle that relationships have
to be invariant under time evolution
relationships of vectors as we learn
that us for a small interval of time the
evolution proceeds by some kind of
hermitian operator H dagger equals H it
doesn't tell us what H is doesn't tell
us what H is but it does tell us
whatever H is it should be hermitian now
hermitian in quantum mechanics means the
object is an observable what are the
implications of it being observable
first of all that it has an orthonormal
basis of eigenstates all of its
eigenvalues are real and it's something
which can be measured in the laboratory
that's what it means to be observable
the postulate of quantum mechanics is
that all hermitian operators correspond
to things that can be observed or
physically interesting quantities that
may be very hard to actually measure but
in principle they should be measurable
and so whatever H is
at some physical quantity the
interpretation of it now we can give it
a name it corresponds its eigenvalues
are the things that you measure when you
measure when you measure H its
eigenvalues have a name they are called
energy we can't see yet at this point
that they correspond to the same
quantities that we define in classical
physics we will have to do some more we
cannot see that no more than we could
see that the momentum the strange
definition of the momentum that we had
what was it - I h-bar D by DX that
operator we identified with momentum I
told you sometime later we will check
that this object behaves like the
classical momentum of a particle when a
wave packet moves in the same sense we
will eventually check
I don't think we'll do it tonight but
will eventually check it not too long a
time that that h or its average value
the expectation value of h the average
of h evolves or behaves exactly the same
way has the same value as the classical
energy of a system approximately the
same value but not for now for now we're
just going to call the eigenvalues the
energy and we're going to call this
object the Hamiltonian so we've learned
a new principle that this is a hermitian
operator called the Hamiltonian which
governs the evolution of a system as it
evolves in time are there any questions
up till now now if we know how a system
evolves for a short period of time that
presumably means we can write some
differential equation governing how the
system evolves with time so let's think
about that
yeah in the classical limit where each
bar goes to zero
you got a divide by zero denominator
well that's the classical limit is
simply the limit in which the energy of
the system is very large in units of H
bar actually it's not energy its energy
times time but epsilon has units of a
time so epsilon times H has units of H
bar but the classical limit is simply
the limit in which this quantity over H
bar is much much bigger than water so
this way this is your a small yeah yeah
we have to ask at the end what's left
over what things have good limits in the
limit that H bar goes to zero I've
written it in a form here we're in the
classical limit when everything is kept
classical H has a good limit all right
but usually we can't see that now for
now that H bar is just an arbitrary
thing that I threw into the formula
about as arbitrary is this H bar which
appears in here in fact it's very
similar H bar okay let's ask now if we
can write a differential equation for
how the state of a system changes with
time let's think about that here's what
we can write we can write sine of T plus
epsilon small change in time from T to T
plus epsilon must equal now on the one
hand it has to equal this U of epsilon
times I but let's not write that let's
just write that it's 1 minus I epsilon H
over H bar within about five minutes
from now I'm going to set H bar equal to
one
wanted to put it in once and for all so
you see where it goes but for the time
being let's leave it eventually I'll
probably set it equal to one it's just a
nuisance to right it's this times sigh
of T okay so to move ahead to push ahead
a little bit in time you apply you you
apply U but U is one minus I epsilon H
over H bar
okay let's manipulate the equation a
little bit first of all the one times I
just gives I and we can transpose it
over to the left hand side so we can
write this as sine of T plus epsilon
minus Phi of T that's taken care of this
and it's taken care of the one here that
is equal the minus I epsilon H over H
bar times I itself now let's divide by
epsilon dividing by epsilon gives us the
left hand side which is obviously a
derivative of sy it's the derivative of
side with respect to time I'm simply
using the formula that a derivative is
the difference divided by the small
change in the argument of the function
in the limit that the small change goes
to zero this is just the derivative I'll
write it as a partial derivative just to
indicate that I'm only changing time
nothing else in the problem the
derivative of Sai with respect to time
is equal to minus i h over h-bar times i
this is telling us how the state changes
if we know the Hamiltonian if we know
the action of the Hamiltonian on every
state then we can predict what it's
going to be in the next instant of time
if we can predict what it's going to be
in the next instant of time we can do
next instant next instant next instant
and build up the entire evolution of the
system this is simply a differential
equation which tells us how side changes
if we know H that this equation has a
name anybody know the name of it that's
the Schrodinger equation
that's the Schrodinger equation it's the
abstract general form of the Schrodinger
equation it's not the equation
Schrodinger wrote down to my knowledge I
think the first one to write it in this
form with Dirac let's multiply it just
let's multiply it by H by little H bar
and by I so if I multiply it by I is IH
bar on the Left I times minus I is plus
1 so I can also write it this way IH bar
DC by DT is the Hamiltonian operator
times I that's sort of very similar to
this formula this said that a derivative
with respect to position is related to
the momentum this says the derivative
with respect to time is related in the
similar way to the energy to the
Hamiltonian notice is a difference in
sign this is purely a convention that
there's a minus sign here and a plus
sign here can everybody see the plus
sign it's in the corner of a that's plus
here I'm going to move it over a little
bit I h-bar
alright that's that's the basic idea of
the Schrodinger equation how systems
evolve with time there's another
equation we can write now this equation
is practically definition not much more
let's put it up here
now let's leave it for a moment we'll
come back to it I was going to write the
eigenvalue equation for H but I'm not
going to do it now all right let's think
about a couple of examples and what this
says how it were actually used to
predict the future so to speak to
predict the future from the present and
to see how it effects measurements of
things let's go back to our simple
system of polarization polarization of
photons okay and let me suppose I have
some sort of material that I've
constructed which shifts the energy of a
photon of a given wavelength depending
on the polarization you know I don't
have to tell you that a photon of the
given wavelength has a certain has a
certain energy energy is related to
wavelength buts but that relationship
can change when the photon moves through
a material right so given the wavelength
you might construct a photon of a given
wavelength in the material it has a
certain energy but that energy might be
different than it would be outside the
material that's that's straightforward
there's nothing spectacular about that
but I might have a material which has a
certain polarization to it so that the
two states of polarization might
actually have different energy from each
other
that's quite conceivable so let's
suppose that the the X&Y polarizations
actually have different energy and we'll
say that the X polarization has energy e
t1 and the Y polarization has energy e2
just to give them names
so we're creatively a material in which
a photon of some particular wavelength
has energy e1 or e2 depending on which
as that can be translated into a
statement about the Hamiltonian it says
that the Hamiltonian is an operator that
has two eigenvalues II 1 and E 2 and
that the two states of polarization are
I gain vectors of that Hamiltonian so
let's write it down it says that H on
I'll tell you what I'm going to call
this one X and this one Y as we did
before on X is equal to e 1 on X X does
not stand for the position now it just
stands for the polarization we're
forgetting entirely the position of the
photon and H on Y is equal to e 2 on Y
all right so the two states of
polarization are being assumed by making
an assumption now I'm making assumption
that whatever the Hamiltonian is that
the X component the X polarization and
the Y polarization are both eigenvectors
with eigenvalue e1 and e2 that's the
material that I've constructed this
particular photon of this particular
wavelength the two polarizations have
different energy what does that imply
about the evolution of this photon as it
moves through the material does it have
any interesting experimental
consequences and we'll see that it does
quite interesting let's begin ok so
let's start with some initial state of
the photon of the photon polarization
let's call it well let's yeah it's sy of
T here's this the way the state vector
of the photon polarization at time T
there's only two states of polarization
and we usually write the X component as
the upper component of a column vector
and the lower component of a column
vector is the Y component so let's just
write that sine of T can be identified
with a column vector alpha of T and beta
of T
alpha of T is the amplitude that the
photon has Expo ler ization beta is the
amplitude that the photon has why
polarization the probability as a
function of time that the photon has
Expo ler ization would be alpha star
alpha and likewise for beta star beta
that would be the polarization
probability to be ye okay everybody
remember this if not tell me now and
I'll ignore you all right so that's sigh
of T and let's write down now the
Schrodinger equation explicitly where is
it we've erased it off the blackboard I
hope I hope not now there it is let's
write down the Schrodinger equation
explicitly and solve it I think I can
think of no better way of illustrating
what it means than to explicitly write
it down and solve it for this very
simple system alright so we begin with I
h-bar let me throw away h-bar now H bar
equals 1 from now on except when I want
to illustrate some point about H bar
itself H bar is equal to 1 from now on
okay so let's write this equation decide
by DT what does that mean that means the
time derivative of this column vector
here the time derivative of the column
vector is just another column vector
whose entries are the time derivatives
alright so the side by DT can just be
identified with a column vector let's
call it alpha dot of T and beta dot of T
dot indicates time derivative as usual
that's Desai by DT let's multiply it by
I naught by H bar H bar Oh set equal to
1 so let's multiply it by I and what
does that equal that equals the
Hamiltonian acting on side first of all
let's write out matrix that's identified
with the Hamiltonian the matrix that's
identified with the Hamiltonian
is just very simple it's just e 2 0 0 e
1 it has eigen vectors x and y with I oh
that's wrong you wanna me to you 1 and E
2 e 1 and E 2 the two eigen vectors the
two eigenvalues are e 1 V 2 and the 2
eigen vectors are just x and y and here
it's displayed in the form of a matrix
ok so let's write down now that this is
equal to H times I H is e 1 0 0 e 2 on
sy and side is just alpha beta ok what
is this equal to the right hand side we
can multiply out the matrix times the
column vector and it's just e 1 alpha e
to beta this is now two differential
equations one for the upper component
and one for the lower component whenever
you get an equation like this you can
read it as several different equations
one for each component let's take the
upper component the upper component
equation that just becomes a perfectly
ordinary equation I times the Alpha by
DT is equal to e 1 alpha that doesn't
work so hard to solve and the lower
equation is very similar I times D beta
by DT is equal to e 2 times beta I think
maybe it would be a little easier and
more recognizable if I would multiply by
minus ie then it would get rid of the I
over here and put a minus I over here
and we'll get rid of the I over here and
put a minus I over here so both
equations that 2 in fact for the simple
example the alphas and the beta's aren't
even coupled together
satisfy separate equations with not even
any mixing between them very simple
equations and the solutions are simple
what's the solution of an equation where
the derivative of an object is
proportional to the object itself or the
coefficient exponential right so the
solution of the first equation here is
that alpha is equal to whatever it is at
time zero alpha of zero in fact let's
call this alpha of T is equal to alpha
of x 0 times e to the minus e to the
minus I P 1 T if I differentiate this
with respect to time
it just pulls down a minus ie 1 which is
exactly what's here ok and let me
simplify the notation by just calling
alpha at time 0 let me just call it
alpha
there's too many too many brackets and
other little pieces of loosens to write
down so which is called alpha is alpha
at time T equals 0 and as time goes on
it just gets multiplied by e to the IET
what about beta of T similar thing
that's equal to beta times e to the
minus ia2
T and so the state of the system is
represented by a column vector we can
write the column vector now as a
function of time alpha e to the minus I
1 T and beta e to the minus I 2 T now
let me just point out at this point
where H bar would have gone had I
included it H bar would go in the
denominator under the EES it will go in
the exponent but as a denominator a 1
over H bar if I had
if I had included it right right so we
see what the energies correspond to they
correspond to phases to two oscillations
in the entries here but different
oscillations for the two entries
different oscillations one with e 1 and
1 with e 2
that's the state of the system after a
time T now let's ask what if we did some
measurements supposing we measured the
polarization of the photon in particular
we measure the photon polarization in
the XY plane
the X versus Y polarization we run it
through an x polarizer we run the photon
through an x polarizer and we find the
probability that it's polarized along
the x axis what's the answer to that
it's just the entry up here the the
square of the entry in the top this one
corresponds to X this one corresponds to
Y the probability that the polarization
that's called probability that the
polarization R is +1 that there's too
many in this EC the probability that the
X polarization is plus in other words
that it's polarized along the x axis
that the photon goes through the
polarizer that's just going to be alpha
e to the minus I Omega D e to the minus
I P 1 T times its own complex conjugate
remember we take these entries and we
multiply them by their own complex
conjugate and what's that going to give
that's just going to give alpha star
alpha
the e to the IET is not going to do
anything when we multiply it by its own
complex conjugate so nothing's happened
I mean this whole business about the
time evolution hasn't done anything
it hasn't changed the probability for X
polarization not even a little bit it's
done nothing to the probability of X
polarization likewise the probability
that's polarized along the y axis is
just beta star beta so our first sight
it seems like this time evolution hasn't
led to any big deal it's done nothing
it's just multiplied the individual
components there by phases but that
hasn't changed any probability the
interesting thing happens when we look
when we decide to use a different
polarizer so let's imagine now that we
took a different polarizer we run it
through after having we take this state
here it is and we run it through not a
vertical horizontal polarizer not an
Expo ler Iser but we run it through a
polarizer that's for example polarized
along the 45 degree axis and ask what's
the probability that the photon goes
through the polarizer at 45 degrees all
right so let's do that let's do that
little calculation
all right first of all the state vector
corresponding to polarization along 45
degrees what is that that corresponds to
the column vector 1 over square root of
2 1 over square root of 2 what do we
have to do we have to take sy the
original sy or not the original side but
sy as it is over here and take its inner
product with the polarization state
polarized the 45 degrees and take the
square of that we'll take the square
soon enough this is called the amplitude
that if we measure the diagonal
polarization what do we call this we had
a name for this uh / the / polarization
but if we measure the / polarization
will either get either go through it
won't go through this is the thing that
gets squared let's not square it yet
this is equal to okay we take the row
vector the bra vector is / and that's
just 1 over square root of 2 1 over
square root of 2 on the other hand after
a time T we have alpha e to the minus ie
1 T beta e to the minus I 2 T and we
have to take the inner product of those
this is very simple it's just equal to 1
over square root of 2 alpha e to the
minus ie 1 T plus beta over square root
of 2 e to the minus I eat uu t that's
the amplitude now what do we have to do
with it in order to get a probability to
get a probability we have to multiply it
by its own complex conjugate we have to
square it here's what's going to happen
here is the point when we when we square
a thing like this there are two kinds of
terms there are the terms coming from
squaring the individual components and
there are the cross terms
let's look at the individual components
the individual components will be alpha
alpha star alpha over 2 and the e to the
I eps will cancel when we multiply this
by its own complex conjugate the e to
the IEP will cancel likewise when we
multiply this by its own complex
conjugate it's the cross term it's the
term gotten from multiplying this by
this which is going to have an
interesting time dependence all right so
let's examine that let's actually
examine it and see what we get but
before we do I want to simplify the
problem a little bit by choosing alpha
and beta in a simple way what I'm going
to do is I'm going to assume that alpha
and beta are equal and both equal to 1
over square root of 2 this corresponds
to the following experiment we send the
photon through a polarizer polarized
along 45 degrees that gives us an
initial state at time T equals zero
which is just polarized of 45 degrees
then it goes downstream in this strange
material where the vertical polarization
states have different energy all right
so two vertical polarizations have
different energy and then we send it
through a second polarizer oriented in
exactly the same direction ordinarily we
would fully expect that we go right
through and with probability one pass
through the second polarizer let's see
if that's true the initial state that
the photon comes out of the polarizer
with is just this is just what it's so
let's call that time T equals zero that
just corresponds to alpha and beta with
no time dependence but let's set alpha
and beta themselves equal to 1 over
square root of 2 so in passing through
this polarizer the photon comes out of
the other side with alpha equals 1 over
square root of 2 and beta equals 1 over
square root of 2 it's just a special
case of this where alpha and beta happen
to be
both themselves one over square root of
two that's how the photon comes out then
the photon propagates for a certain time
T until it gets to the other polarizer
that's what we have here we can now like
this we can specialize it to the case
one over square root of 2 1 over square
root of 2 so here's how the photon came
out it propagated downstream for a time
T and then we want to know what's the
probability that it passes through the
second polarizer polarized exactly the
same way as the first polarizer so this
becomes one-half here and this also
becomes one-half I'm just doing this to
put some numbers in just put some
numbers in to see what comes out all
right so this is now the amplitude that
the photon passes through the second
polarizer let's calculate the
probability the probability is simply
this times its own complex conjugate no
there were 2 square roots of 2 here yup
right ok so let's see what comes out we
have we're going to have 1/2 times 1/2
when I square this let's pull out the
factor of 1/2 and square it and then
we're going to have e to the I minus I 1
T plus e to the minus ie 2t
all times e to the plus I II 1 t plus e
to the plus I eetu T this bracket is
simply the complex conjugate of this
bracket so the 1/2 times 1/2 that's just
squaring the overall factor of 1/2 here
and then I've multiplied this by its own
complex conjugate the whole thing is
then 1/4 and let's see what we get e to
the minus IET II 1 T times e to the I e
1 T that's 1
this one times this one is one
alright we're finished with that let's
let's mark off as we as we do them
taking care of this product now let's
take care of this product that's one
again so that's plus two then we have to
cross terms and the two cross terms are
let's see what they are they're e to the
minus ie one T times e to the plus I eat
Ooty
so that's e to the I II to minus e 1 T
and the other term is simply the complex
conjugate of this plus e to the I II -
II well it's right over to the - I eat
ooh - II won t
I think it's a little bit helpful to
define e to minus e1 what is e2 minus e1
it's the difference of energy of the two
polarization States
notice that the answer only depends on
the energy difference of the two
polarization states this is deep
important physics only depends on energy
differences nothing would change if you
added a constant to the energy of a
system all right so it only depends as
as we might have guessed in the first
place it only depends on the energy
differences let's call the energy
difference eetu minus e1 let's call it
Delta e just so I can stop writing e1
and e2 let's call it Delta e the
difference of the energy of the X
polarization and the Y polarization okay
what is e to the I something plus e to
the minus I times that same thing e to
the i-x plus e to the minus I X just
twice the cosine so this whole thing is
just I can now erase all the
Exponential's and it just becomes twice
the cosine of Delta e times T let's
write that out twice the cosine plus
twice the cosine of Delta e times T ok
let's review what we did we have a
material which gives different energies
to the vertical and horizontal polarizer
polarizations we then sent through the
material we sent through a polarizer a
photon to polarize it along the 45
degree axis and then we waited a while
we went downstream aways and after a
time T the photon is sent through a
second polarizer oriented exactly the
same direction as the first one and we
ask what's the probability that it goes
through here it is and notice that it
oscillates as a function of time it also
lates with a frequency which is
determined by the energy difference
if we were to plot this function we
plotted the function well what is it
it's 1/2 the quarters mixer this is 1/2
plus 1/2 cosine Delta et it's a function
at time T equals 0 1/2 plus 1/2 is 1 or
what's the meaning of that time T equals
zero would correspond to putting the
second polarizer close enough to the
first polarizer that nothing much
happens no time evolution between them
if the time evolution between them is no
time at all
then the photons surely goes through the
second polarizer there's been no time
for the state to change and so if it
goes through two parallel polarisers the
probability to get through the second
one is 1 that's 1 plus 1 1/2 plus 1/2
but then some time evolves and after a
time delta e times whatever it is the
probability has actually gone to 0 that
it gets through the second polarizer it
looks like this doesn't get negative
never gets negative probabilities can't
get negative it just oscillates going
from 1 to 0 to 1 to 0 to 1 to 0 of
course when it goes to 0 that's an
indication that it will definitely pass
through the polarizer at at 90 degrees
so the polarization of the photon after
a certain time has rotated it's
basically rotated if we wait enough time
until we come to the 0 over here then
it's certain that it will pass through
this polarizer so the polarization has
rotated it's not a circularly polarized
Photon but the polarized the linear
polarization has rotated and it just
keeps rotating as you go downstream so
this funny material which splits the
energy of the two photons has the effect
has a real physical effect that is the
real physical effect of
the polarization to rotate as you go
downstream that of course is observable
so this is kind of interesting if we
measure not the horizontal vertical
polarization there's no effect on that
there was no effect on the probabilities
for the horizontal and vertical
polarization but we find an interesting
effect on the probabilities for the for
the slash polarizations that's the
that's the basic phenomenon and this is
an interference phenomena this is
interference of probability amplitudes
causing these oscillations destructive
interference over here constructive
interference over here and this is all
with a single photon or any questions
about the about up till now
this material has to be completely
filling this space yeah materials
filling the space between the polarisers
and it goes on and on forever in every
direction don't ask me how to make the
material I haven't thought about it very
hard I'm sure if we went into the
laboratory and asked the technician me
hmm what what's that magic material if
we went in esteves the the technician
and the lab here we probably pull out a
piece of something and it probably got
some mean time on that yeah time on the
x-axis the material in that state goes
to zero well let's do some precise
language the probability that it passes
through the other polarizer in the same
direction has gone to zero that's the
thing to say well how far downstream you
put the other polarizer remember the
photon moves with a certain velocity and
so the velocity determines how much time
yeah for our simple purposes here we can
just identify the distance downstream
with the time in some appropriate way
yeah since we're not very much worried
about the actual motion of the photon
only the motion of its polarization so
isolating out the polarization we can
then identify the climb downstream with
the velocity of the other photon which
may or may not be the speed of light in
this strange material well it is the
speed of light in the strange material
excuse me
that's an interesting question I don't
know I'm not sure I suspect it would
cause yeah I would suspect that we cause
an oscillation back and forth between
the two polarization between the two
circular polarizations but this is
something you can do all right all we
have to do is put an eye down here okay
so let's now let's do it let's let's it
we'll just put an eye over here it'll
put an eye over here so there will be an
eye over here and a minus I over here
what will that do oh it looks like it
will change yeah it looks like it'll
turn this into sign but it will leave
the oscillation yeah thank you it was
good you you arbitrarily choosing you
know x and y this way I still live this
way and yeah it seems to change
everything
well we haven't we have a material which
was constructed in a certain factory and
we've lined it up
so a certain factory it has two axes in
it they're really thin if you looked at
it through a microscope you would
discover some axes and we simply lie
those axes off of the X&Y material
itself yeah the point is the you get an
effect when the material itself is
misaligned with the polarisers it's
misaligned with the polarizes then you
see something interesting happen you see
the rotation of the polarization or the
oscillation between the two states of
circular polarization so the sign here
when you when you put an eye in here
would also cause an oscillation of the
probabilities it would look the same
except it would start at zero and go up
to a maximum and so forth it would
correspond to an oscillation between two
circular two states of circular
polarization probably becoming
elliptically polarized in between
yeah that's what would happen you would
have a circular polarization and the
circular polarization I think in the
vertical direction would become
elliptically polarized and then come out
afterwards rotating in the opposite
direction as you went downstream but the
main point is that are that there are
these interference phenomena which
really do happen just because of these
phases notice something else if the two
phases were the same if e1 equally - if
they were exactly the same then this
Delta e would be zero and cosine of zero
is just 1 so this would just be 1 plus 1
is 1 and in other words if the two
energies were the same then it would
behave as if there was no material in
there at all which is the same thing
when we use the ex polarizer to measure
the ex polarization state now you get
that cosine 0 yeah yeah yeah but if the
twenties are the same you get no effect
on anything no matter what the
orientation the polarizer czar does
nothing yeah so adding the same energy
to both polarization states does nothing
and that's a that's a very general
property of quantum mechanics that if
you add a constant number to the energy
of every state it does nothing there has
no effect whatever on anything
interesting that you can measure so
that's why only energy differences are
relevant in physics ok um now let's
let's do one more thing before we take a
break we're gonna take a break and
probably go home but let's do one other
thing one interesting thing here that
let's suppose we have some observable
some observable I need a letter K K for
observable K is an operator I'll put a
little hat on it but I'll probably
forget it after a while and I'm
interested in its expectation value its
average value
let's take its average value in the
states I we can just call that the
average of K if we want to be even a
little bit looser we might just call it
K which of course will be wrong to call
it K because it's just the central value
it's just the app this is the average
value of K if the probability
distribution is nice and peaked then
most of the times we would measure K
somewheres near the probabilities near
the expectation value somewheres near
the average value I want to write this
this is too this is too loose for me all
right
oh just Corte how does this change with
time K is some very definite operator it
represents some specific observable I
want to take the same observable and ask
how its value changes with time so it
could be the momentum it could be the
position or it could be one of the
observables associated with the
polarization and I want to know how it
changes the time for example it could
correspond to the observable associated
with with Slash the polarization states
we had worked it out it was some
definite operator we might ask how it
changes with time so I would like to
calculate the time derivative of psy k
scy why does it change it changes
because the size change with time
right the state vectors of the system
change the time we're going to take a
fixed observable so we're not going to
take change the observable that we're
talking about it might correspond to
some specific polarization state we're
not going to change it but we're going
to ask how it changes because the state
of the system changes with time so I'd
like to calculate that well this is just
a product it's a product of sigh
basically the complex conjugate of sy sy
over here with the K in the sandwich in
between but the thing inside the Bologna
in the sandwich doesn't change with time
only the bread on the outside changes
with time so we have a product to
calculate the derivative the time
derivative of a product to calculate the
time derivative of product is just a sum
of two terms one term having to do with
the time derivative of the bra the other
term having to do with the time
derivative of the cat so we can write
this out this is just a straightforward
product rule for derivatives this is
equal to we first time differentiate the
ket and that gives us sy k and I'm not
going to write this IDT I'm just going
to right side dot and then we have
another term where the bra vector is
differentiated and that's plus side dot
k scy well where do we get these side
dots from platform the fact that we have
we erased them off the blackboard okay
so let's see let me write there I'm a
Schrodinger equation we get them from
the Schrodinger equation so the
Schrodinger equation is that I decide by
DT
I decide by DT which is also called side
dot let's just call it side that is
equal to H sigh do I have the sign
correct yes I do you can put this we can
put the the I on the other side minus I
sine dot is minus IH sigh all right we
need to we'll also need the
corresponding equation for the bra
vector so I got is equal to plus I bar
vector sy times H okay when you act on
bra vectors you act from the right when
you act on ket vectors you act from the
left this equation here is just a
complex conjugate of this equation I've
changed the sign of the I because the
complex conjugate I you have to change
its sign all right so we have only
material we need we have side dot water
side doc side that is minus IH on sigh
so let's put a minus I here and instead
of writing side that we can write H
times I
well what about this equation over here
this equation here we use the bra vector
version of it plus I and we have to put
the H next to the sy so let's put the H
next to the sy and I think it's plus I
well we have two terms which look very
similar but the h and the K come in the
opposite order so what we actually have
here is minus I times the expectation
value of the commutator of catch with
width of K with H
what is a commutator the commutator of K
with H this definition is just K H - H K
we've done these things before we've
done commutator z' of position and
momentum we've done commutator z' of
some of the polarization operators is k
with h so we've learned something
interesting we've learned that the time
derivative sorry the time derivative of
the expectation value of a quantity is
simply minus i times the expectation
value of the same object the commutator
of that object with the Hamiltonian it's
the Hamiltonian which determines how
things evolve with time let's so let's
condense the equation here fundamental
theorem about how things change in
quantum mechanics this is equal a race
that night or in the board it was minus
I R plus I minus I but now it depends on
let's just write it this way
let's expectation value of K the time
derivative of it is minus I times the
expectation value of the commutator now
is it h of k with k okay with h k with h
right so to find out our thing changes
at the time you commute it with the
Hamiltonian let me just remind you that
in classical mechanics what you do if
you want to find out how a thing changes
with time
is you take the Poisson bracket with the
Hamiltonian in both cases it's the
Hamiltonian which tells you how things
change how they change with time ah
quantum mechanics it's the commutator
and classical mechanics it's the Poisson
bracket now in fact Poisson brackets and
commutator z' are very close to each
other they're very closely connected and
we'll talk about that connection but for
now and this was a very easy derivation
this was very simple what did we do let
me just remind you what we did we time
differentiated this by time
differentiating bra vector and adding to
it the time derivative of the ket vector
and then we just used the Schrodinger
equation for the time derivative of the
ket vector and the time derivative of
the bra vector the opposite sign which
appears here because of the complex
conjugate wound up giving us a
commutator so they're two lines two
lines basically to derive the connection
between time derivatives and
commentator's with Hamiltonians we could
well I didn't I didn't know we could
apply this to the problem of the
polarization and see how the expectation
value of polarization would change as
the photon move downstream I'm not going
to do that because said I'm have it in
my notes let's take a break for a few
minutes so we've proved the theorem that
said that the time derivative of any
expectation value is related to a
certain commutator commutator of the
Hamiltonian with the quantity in
question an implication of that is that
if a quantity K commutes with the
Hamiltonian in other words if the
commutator is zero then the time
derivative of its expectation value is
exactly zero exactly zero in any state
in any state the time derivative of the
expectation value will be zero if the
community
FK with H is equal to zero so that's the
condition for a conserved quantity you
can prove a stronger theorem I won't do
it tonight this is simply a theorem
about the expectation value of K I'd
like to prove a somewhat stronger
theorem the stronger theorem might say
that the probability distribution or the
probability for a given value of K
doesn't change with time it's also true
but for the time being I'll simplify the
theorem the expectation value doesn't
change if the object commutes with the
Hamiltonian and that at least at the
level of expectation values is a
statement that any quantity which
commutes with the Hamiltonian is
conserved right certainly the
implication goes the other way if a
quantity is conserved it must then its
expectation value is time independent
definitely and in that case it must
commute with the Hamiltonian the
implication goes in both directions if a
quantity is conserved it commutes with
the Hamiltonian if a quantity commutes
with the Hamiltonian then it's conserved
but one special case is the Hamiltonian
itself any operator commutes with itself
any operator commutes with itself a
times a is equal to a times a and it
doesn't matter which way you put the A's
in so it implies that the Hamiltonian
itself is conserved the Hamiltonian is
some kind of conserved quantity let me
just point out the classical analog the
classical analog is that the Poisson
bracket of any quantity with itself is
also zero what would that be let's take
some opera object AE a with B that's the
a by the X DB by B cube of the sorry by
DP minus da by DP the B by DX that's the
plus own bracket of a with B if a and B
are equal then obviously this is equal
to zero the a by DX is the same as DB by
DX and the B by DP is the same as the a
by DP so that this is equal to zero
again in classical physics of follows
that
any quantity whose Poisson bracket with
the Hamiltonian is equal to zero is
conserved its time derivative is equal
to zero and in particular the
Hamiltonian is a quantity which commute
AR sorry is a quantity whose Poisson
bracket with itself is equal to zero and
so it follows that the Hamiltonian is
conserved in quantum mechanics it's the
commutator but same statement if a
quantity commutes with it if quantity
commutes with the Hamiltonian over it
requiring Li commutes with the
Hamiltonian is conserved the Hamiltonian
commutes with the Hamiltonian
Hamiltonian control what is that
Hamiltonian it's the energy so this is
the principle of energy conservation
coming out of just spontaneously coming
out of basic formalism of quantum
mechanics there may or may not be other
quantities which commute with the
Hamiltonian if there are they are also
conserved let's now come to a particle
on the line particle moving on a line
now what is the connection well first of
all let's just have a particle moving on
a line no potential energy no forces on
the particle for simplicity then the
particle is described either by a wave
function which depends on its position
or the Fourier transform which depends
on momentum size star of X times I of X
is the probability to find the particle
located somewhere Zeist outside twiddle
of p time sorry start Whittle of P is
the probability that has a given
momentum okay how do we apply this idea
the Schrodinger equation idea to the
wave function of a particle again the
rules are exactly the same we would like
to find some way of thinking about the
time derivative of sigh of X and T with
respect to T
right now what we're doing is we're
doing the analog of what we did before
instead of writing a state vector sigh
of T I'm just writing a corresponding
wave function sigh of X which also
depends on time wave functions depend on
time if they didn't depend on time
everything would be frozen and so for a
particle on a line the state vector can
simply be replaced by a wave function
which depends on X and T or its Fourier
transform which depends on momentum and
also T how do they evolve with time they
must evolve with time by the same set of
rules minus I times some hermitian
operator still call the Hamiltonian
acting on sy of X and T same set of
arguments and I simply just removed the
brackets here just by remembering that
functions are vectors functions of X are
vectors so I don't need a little bit
redundant for me to put a ket symbol
around this since we remember that
functions are a vector space all right
now what what operator what operators do
we have around well we can multiply side
by functions of X that's something we
can do
so just multiplying by some function of
X is a linear operator and we can
differentiate side we can do all sorts
of operations involving multiplying by
functions of X differentiating with
respect to X they're all linear
operators they're all linear operators
on these I of X's here for example just
multiplying by X that's the operator
that corresponds to position what about
the collar operator that corresponds to
momentum that's minus I D by DX let's
put the h-bar into this minus I h-bar D
by DX that's momentum ok what do we know
we know classically now classically is
not a different theory classical physics
is the limit of quantum mechanics for
rather heavy objects which are heavy
enough that quantum mechanics is not
important for them but it's a limit of
quantum mechanics it's kind of a special
case of quantum mechanics in a certain
limit what do we know
classically about the motion of a
particle on a line we know that the
energy which we can also think of as the
Hamiltonian classically but we know that
the energy E which I'll also remind you
is the Hamiltonian is one for it's
related to the momentum it's the square
of the momentum divided by twice the
mass of the particle I've simply used
kinetic energy is one-half m velocity
squared and momentum is M times velocity
just solve this equation for the
velocity plug it back into here and the
answer is P squared over 2m that
suggests does not prove you can never
prove something about quantum mechanics
from the classical physics you can
suggest or you can if you like say the
the classical limit has an energy which
is P squared over 2m a suggestion and a
guess is that the quantum mechanical
Hamiltonian is also P squared over 2m
what is P squared over 2m mean in the
quantum mechanical context let's let's
guess now P squared over twice the mass
but now this P is an operator what does
this mean what does P P is minus I D by
DX so if it was just P that appeared
here we would just write minus ID by DX
and this would be a differential
equation for sy what is P squared mean P
squared means P times P when you
multiply operators it simply means you
multiply the operator you if you apply
it to a wave function you multiply you
first
apply the first operator and then you
apply the second operator so here's what
P squared means P squared on sy of X
means minus I h-bar D by DX being
applied to - I decide by the X this is P
acting on sy and he is P acting on the
result that's just P squared on side
okay so now we can write the Schrodinger
equation the Schrodinger equation just
becomes a minus I P squared
what's P squared minus I times minus I
is another minus sign it looks like to
me
ah missing an H bar H bar squared second
derivative of sine with respect to X so
this means a by DX times decide by the X
is the second derivative of sine of
respect X that's it I squared there ah
yeah I squared I squared which is the
minus sign almost no more I give it a
nice burger is there - yeah - I -
plus I got - yeah t squared is minus I
on the - Ari planks right just a - back
first time wait so the my decide from
here right - I - here
privacy is and then P squared which
gives me another - yeah I think I got
the time I think I have it right in the
first place
you should put an H bar the Schrodinger
equation where oh good good good
yes you're absolutely right so I think
I'm just going to do it over again let's
just do it over again let's do it over
again keep all the factors okay so our
basic rule is that I decide I h-bar I
h-bar the side by DT is equal to H sigh
right whatever right is that what I told
you in the beginning yeah all right IH
bar times this IV T now what is H H is P
squared over 2m and P each factor of P 1
over 2m each factor of P is minus I
h-bar D by DX we have two of them
there's another minus I h-bar D by DX
I'm sorry
so altogether the right hand side is 1
over 2m I have the feeling I've still
lost a minus sign no no okay 1 over 2m h
bar squared minus I times minus I is
minus 1 and these seconds are
our VX squared right now you'll get a
minus i when you bring the that's equal
to IH bar decide by DT and if I like I
could divide away the H bar here so we
get one H bar on the right hand side and
then if I like I can multiply this by -
I get rid of the I over here and then
I'll get what plus I plus I on the side
plus I on the side I don't see any
particular well okay let's do it so we
get plus I on the side that's some this
is the Schrodinger equation for a free
particle for a free particle on a line
with no forces on it and we'll come to
forces next time but for particle on a
line with no forces on it this tells us
how the wave function changes with time
the basic principles are exactly the
same as for the power for the
polarization the Hamiltonian has to be a
hermitian operator incidentally you
might ask how do I know the Hamiltonian
is a hermitian operator well the square
of any hermitian operator is also
hermitian that's easy to prove so P
squared is as hermitian as P itself is
and we'd already proved that P was
hermitian so P squared over 2m is a
hermitian hamiltonian perfectly good it
does stand for the energy and this is
the Schrodinger equation with all of its
H bars and eyes in place next time I
think well let's see maybe we can still
solve it yeah let's so let's solve it
let's solve it while we're at it
in particular let's look for solutions
of this equation which are eigenvectors
of the momentum operator in other words
let's look to see what how the time
dependence works for eigenvectors of the
other momentum operator eigenvectors of
the momentum operator are just e to the
I P X P is the eigenvalue so I put the H
bars in I guess I should put the H bars
in since I've kept them around P over H
bar X P is a number it represents the
momentum it represents the eigenvalue of
p square of the momentum operator we've
done this before
e to the I P over H bar X those
represent wave functions which have
definite momentum alright now we can do
something to this and still have it of
the form e to the I P H bar over X we
can multiply it by a number it's still
an eigen vector of momentum in fact we
can multiply it by a time-dependent
number a function of T it still is an
eigen that every instant of time it's
still an eigen vector of the momentum
when I differentiate with respect to X
this f of T is just a complete spectator
and so when I calculate what the
momentum operator does the F of T is a
complete spectator it does nothing at
all and this is still an eigen vector at
each instant of time this is an eigen
vector of the of the momentum operator
why did I put this F of T there because
without the F of T there would be no
time dependence to it and I'm looking at
them and I know that there has to be a
time dependence
I'm decided by DT is going to be
whatever this is equal to so let's see
if we can figure out what this f of T is
here all we have to do is apply the
Schrodinger equation to it let's first
calculate this side this is the society
here sigh of T
no I don't think there is I don't think
there is
okay so let's calculate the side by DT
when I want to differentiate with
respect to time only F gets
differentiated so side dot is equal to F
dot times e to the I P over H bar X
that's the left side of the Schrodinger
equation now let's take the right side
of Schrodinger equation that's equal to
I h-bar over 2 m and now the second
derivative of side with respect to x
squared each time I differentiate with
respect to X the F of course that's just
a spectator nothing happens to it this
stays there now we have to differentiate
the e to the IPX twice with respect to X
each time you differentiate it pulls
down an IP over H bar so that gives us
an I P over H bar squared times e to the
I P over H bar X ok let's see what we
have both sides of the equation have e
to the I P over H bar X in them we can
cancel that off let's cancel that off
the rest of it is just a function for
just an equation for F and it says that
f dot the time derivative F is just
let's see there is two powers of I here
that's a minus one and another I here so
that's minus I how many H bars in the
denominator so this is a 2m H bar in the
denominator there's a P squared upstairs
and in F is that it is it right I think
that's all there is
no I cancelled one of the H bars in the
denominator with the H bar in the top is
2h bars in the denominator because there
was two peas so HP came with an H bar
yeah I think it's right okay so here we
have an equation for F it says that time
derivative F is a certain number complex
number times F what's the solution an
exponential and here it is F is equal to
e to the minus I P squared over 2m I'll
put the H bar next to the I there times
T I've discovered what F is and my whole
solution then is e to the I P over H bar
X minus I P squared over 2m H bar times
T that's it that's that's the solution
of the Schrodinger equation
corresponding to a momentum eigenstate
notice that it changes with time but it
changes with time in a very very simple
way it changes with time with a pure
phase what does that say about the
probably okay we're now talking about a
particular momentum eigenstate we're not
talking about a superposition of
momentum eigenstates yet this is some
specific momentum eigenstate and that's
how it varies with time
I think I think we'll quit here and come
back to this next time we can ask
various probability there are questions
we can ask for example does the
probability for a given momentum vary
with time there's the probability for a
given position vary with time but we
will deal with that next time
incidentally you might want to prove to
yourself that the momentum commutes with
the Hamiltonian the momentum P commutes
with the Hamiltonian P squared over 2m
that's a little exercise and that
exercise proves that momentum is
conserved
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu